Finding aid to the Sophia Satina Papers CA.MS.00336
Smith College Archives
Sophia Satina Papers
1922-1978
Smith College Archives
Satina, Sophia, 1879-1975
CA.MS.00336
0.417 linear feet (1 container)
Professor of Botany. Contains correspondence, clippings, publications, photographs, and scrapbook.
Biographical / Historical
Sophie Satin (Sophia Satina) was born on April 17, 1879 in Tambov, Russia, a town just south of Moscow. Satin, an ardent advocate for women's education during the Tsarist regime, was a graduate of the first class to matriculate at the Women's University in Moscow. She continued to be involved with the University, becoming an assistant professor in the Department of Botany, a position she held until her departure from Russia in 1921. Prior to her emigration, Satin and a few of her colleagues opened a botanical museum in Moscow that was free to the public. The museum was active until the Bolsheviks staged a revolution in 1917. Satin, an activist and feminist, fled to the United States in response to the new regime and began researching at the Carnegie Research Laboratories in Cold Springs Harbor, New York. In 1943, Satin acquired a position at Smith College working under famed Geneticist Albert Blakeslee as a research assistant in the Genetics Experimental Station (G.E.S.). While Satin did not hold a Ph.D., she became a visiting associate professor of Botany, and assistant director of the G.E.S. She worked at the college until her retirement in 1955. Through her work, Satin helped lay the foundations for growing the fungus penicillium, and in 1944 was awarded an Honorary Doctorate in Science from Smith College. Satin died on February 24, 1975 in New York City.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains biographical information regarding Sophie Satin, correspondence, photographs, publications, and a retirement tribute (in the form of a scrapbook) for Satin.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Sophia Satina papers were donated to the Smith College Archives from a number of sources.
Satina, Sophia, 1879-1975; Satina, Sophia, 1879-1975
- Biographical information, 1948-1976 (Box 1005, Folder 1)
- Award and degree information, 1943-1944 (Box 1005, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1944-1976 (Box 1005, Folder 3)
- Retirement tribute, 1955 (Box 1005, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1922-1978 (Box 1005, Folder 5)
- Publications
  - "Education of Women in Pre-Revolutionary Russia" (English), 1966 (Box 1005, Folder 6)
  - "Education of Women in Pre-Revolutionary Russia" (Russian), 1966 (Box 1005, Folder 7)
  - "Recollections" (English), Early 1970s (Box 1005, Folder 8)
  - "Recollections" (Russian), Early 1970s (Box 1005, Folder 9)
  - "Reminiscences of Rachmaninoff" (Russian), 1946 (Box 1005, Folder 10)
  - Publications and publication information, 1943-1954 (Box 1005, Folder 11)
- Scrapbook (retirement tribute), 1955 (Box 1005)